Bolta Rubber Company Photographs 6543 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Bolta Rubber Company Photographs
1930-1939
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Bolta Rubber Company
6543 P
0.33 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Photographs of employees and machinery in the production of rubber goods.
10062522
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 06, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 09, 2017
Scope and Contents
Includes images of the buffing room, calendering room, and combing room. There are also several photographs of employees, both inside and outside the factory. Three of the photographs show the demolition of building no.16.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5012: Saul Wallen Papers
Belts and belting; Employees -- Women; Factories; Labor--Female; Rubber goods; Rubber industry and trade; Rubber industry workers; Rubber machinery; Textile industry--Massachusetts; Textile machinery; Textile workers; Lawrence (Mass.); Bolta Rubber Company.
10062522
- Machinery, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: What makes the wheels go round, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Saunders Studio, 467 Essex Street, Lawrence, Mass. photographers. Image depicts the rubber belting that was produced (?) by the Bolta Rubber Co., Lawrence, Mass., which manufactured hard rubber goods. 20 x 24 cm.
    Format: Black and White photograph.
  - Item 2: Rubber mill, 1931; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image shows male worker in overalls at machinery, who appears to be handling a roll of rubber. Machinery made by Vaughn, probably the Vaughn Machinery Co. of Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio, which made vulcanizing presses. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 26 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 3: Fixers room, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    193-?. Image shows interior room of mill with unidentified machinery. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 18 x 12.5 cm.
  - Item 4: Machine shop, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    193-?. Image shows machine shop in mill, with male employees engaged at various machines. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
- Buffing Room, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Comb buffing wheel, 1934; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1934. Image depicts the interior of the mill, with comb buffing wheels visible. Note the fancy stools in front of each machine. See item 2 in this folder for a photo of employees at the comb buffing wheels. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 2: Comb buffing room, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    193-?. Image depicts comb buffing room in the mill, where female employees sit at the comb buffing wheels. See item 1 in this folder for a photo of the wheels without employees. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24.5 x 19 cm.
  - Item 3: Wheel buffing machine, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    193-?. Image depicts a wheel buffing macine. This was an old style feed roll unit showing the application ofr wax. Female operator is identified on reverse of photo as Nellie Guthrie. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 20.5 x 25.25 cm.
  - Item 4: Another view of comb buffing room, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    193-?. Image depicts female employees at comb buffing machines. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount). Number of machines and employees smaller than in folder 5, item 1 photograph.
  - Item 5: Automation comes to the buffing room, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    193-?. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 19 cm.
  - Item 6: Remodeled old-style feed head buffing machine, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    193-?. Image depicts female employee (identified on reverse of photo as Hilda Alfond) at buffing machine. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 25 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 7: Transfer between comb buffing machines, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Saunders Studio, 467 Essex Street, Lawrence, Mass. photographers. Image shows interior of mill room with two machines linked by a conveyor belt (note the combs on the conveyor belt). The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 8: Automatic comb buffing machine, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image shows interior of mill room with automatic comb buffing machine; note box with finished combs in foreground. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
- Calendering Room, 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: No. 1 Springfield boiler, 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Saunders Studio, 467 Essex Street, Lawrence, Mass., October 30, 1936. Image depicts construction of brick area around boiler (boiler itself is not visible). The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 26 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 2: Transformers for No. 1 cal'd (calender?), Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    193-?. Image shows several transformers lined up outside a mill building; note the workhorse at the far left. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 19 cm.
  - Item 3: No. 1 cal'd (calender?) mill line, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    No. 1 cal'd (calender?) mill line. 193-?. Image shows machinery loaded onto a flatbed railroad car outside the mill building; three men stand off to the right. The machinery was made by Vaughn, probably the Vaughn Machinery Co. of Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio, which made vulcanizing presses. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25 x 18 cm. (w/mount). See item 4 in this folder for a photo of the machinery in place in the mill.
  - Item 4: Drive - No. 1 cal'd (calender?) rubber mill line, Building no.3, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    193-?. Image shows machinery from item 3 in this folder in place inside mill. Machinery made by Vaughn, probably the Vaughn Machinery Co. of Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio, which made vulcanizing presses. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 26.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 5: Press room and calendering room, Building no.3, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    193-?. Image shows interior of mill room with presses; workmen and supervisors (?) visible in background. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 19.5 cm.
- Comb Packing, 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Comb packing room, 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    about 1936. Image shows interior of mill room where female employees pack combs. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 2: Another view of the comb packing room, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    193-?. Image shows another view of the comb packing room. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 18 x 12.5 cm. Smaller and has few employees than the view in item 1 of this folder.
- Demolition of Building 16, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Wiring an unsafe wall, Building no.16, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Saunders Studio, Lawrence, Mass. photographers. 193-?. Image shows exterior of mill partially demolished, with workman balanced on part of wall, attaching wiring; other workmen on the ground assist. Note long ladders in use and steel framework partially visible behind wall. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 25 x 20 cm. First of three photos marking demolition of this wall; see items 2 and 3 in this folder.
  - Item 2: Wall coming down, Building no.16, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Saunders Studio, Lawrence, Mass. photographers. 193-?. Image shows the upper half of an exterior mill coming down during demoliton. Note piles of stone debris on ground and steel framework partially visible behind wall. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 20 x 25 cm. Second of three photos marking demolition of this wall; see items 1 and 3 in this folder.
  - Item 3: Wall demolished, Building no.16, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Saunders Studio, Lawrence, Mass. photographers. 193-?. Image shows the upper half of an exterior mill has now been demolished. Note piles of stone debris on ground and steel framework that is now more fully visible behind wall. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 25 x 20 cm. Third of three photos marking demolition of this wall; see items 1 and 2 in this folder.
- Employees and Automobiles, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: A local trucking company, 1930; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Image shows pickup truck outside the Bolta Rubber Company in Lawrence, Mass. Note the rear part of an expensive car to the right; see item 2 in this folder for a better view. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 12.5 x 13 cm.
  - Item 2: 1930 gas guzzler, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Image shows automobile in foreground; expensive automobile in the background outside the office of the Bolta Rubber Company in Lawrence, Mass. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 19.5 x 19 cm.
  - Item 3: Employees outside office, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Image shows employees outside the office of the Bolta Rubber Company in Lawrence, Mass. The employees are identified (on the reverse) from left, as Bob Kesler, Mr. Houston, Lydia Halbech. The photograph is dated 1931 on the reverse, but Kesler and Halbech do not appear in the Lawrence city directories until 1936, he as a clerk at the company and she as a stenographer. Her clothing also suggests a date later in the '30s. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 19.5 x 23.5 cm.
  - Item 4: Group of employees, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    193-?. Image shows group of unidentified male employees taken inside room with tubing equipment on the left. Presumably the Bolta Rubber Company in Lawrence, Mass. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 9 x 6.5 cm.
- Press Foundation, 1931; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Press foundation., Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 7)
    193-?. Image depicts the construction of the foundation to support the press. Two men standing to the right, one in suit, tie and hat, the other in duster over a suit (foreman or supervisor?). The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 2: Press foundation, Building no.3, 1931; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Saunders Studio, 467 Essex Street, Lawrence, Mass. Image depicts construction of foundation for press; open section on floor with lumber framework partially visible. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
- Tin Line, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Tin line, Building no.3, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    193-?. Image depicts unspecified machinery made by Farrel-Birmingham, a foundry in Conn. The photograph was probably taken in situ by Farrel-Birmingham; note the Farrel-Birmingham stamp in the lower right corner. See item 3 in this folder for a closeup view of the tin line. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 19 cm.
  - Item 2: Pressing hard rubber combs, 1932; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    mage depicts male employee pressing hard rubber combs. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 26 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 3: Closeup view of tin line, 1931; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Image depicts closeup view of unspecified machinery made by Farrel-Birmingham, a foundry in Conn. The photograph was probably taken in situ by Farrel-Birmingham; note the Farrel-Birmingham stamp in the lower right corner.The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 24 x 19 cm. See item 1 in this folder for a wider view of the tin line.
  - Item 4: Pressing hard rubber combs, 1932; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Image depicts male employee pressing hard rubber combs. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. Copy B. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 5: Tin line - hard rubber combs, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    193-?. Image depicts male employee (with back to camera) standing in front of machine where a reel of tin unspools. The Bolta Rubber Co. of Lawrence, Mass., manufactured hard rubber goods. 23.5 x 18 cm. (w/out mount); 25.5 x 18 cm. (w/mount).